Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is קיי"ב Kuf Yud
Beis and 112, the penultimate דף daf of the מסכת. masechet. We
pick up on קיי"א עמוד ב', Kuf Yud Aleph Amud Bais, the
second of the widest lines. The גמרא Gemara after the משנה. Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah
basically after first saying that the people of the עיר הנדחת Ir
Nidachas don't have a portion in עולם הבא, Olam Ha-Ba, it went
on to finally deal with all of the הלכות halachos that relate
to what makes a city an עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas as opposed
to just many individuals who worship עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tana Rabbanan, the
גמרא Gemara gets straight to the הלכה. halachah. יצאו, Yatzu, ולא שלוחים.
v'lo sheluchim. So יצאו אנשים בני בליעל מקרבך, yatzu anashim b'nei b'liya'al
mi-kirbecha, men, people who are wicked people went from its midst. So
they went, not representatives. It has to be the people themselves that
are doing it, not people that represent them, that are enticing the
people to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. אנשים, Anashim, people, אין אנשים פחות
משנים. ein anashim pachas mi-shnayim. So there has to be at least
two of them. דבר אחר, Davar acher, אנשים ולא נשים, anashim v'lo
nashim, men not women. אנשים ולא קטנים, anashim v'lo k'tanim, not minors.
בני בליעל, B'nei B'liya'al, people like wicked people, בנים שפרקו עול שמים,
banim she-porku ol shamayim, בלי עול, b'li ol, they've cast off the
yoke of heaven מצואריהם mi-tzavareihem from their necks. מקרבך, Mi-kirbecha, so from
its midst. I'm not exactly sure by the way what the בליעל
b'liya'al does in terms of
halachically or what that's adding, but anyway it's just explaining what that
word means. From its midst, ולא מן הספר. v'lo min ha-s'far. So
it has to be a city that is in the middle of
the land, not a city that is on the border because a
border city, if that becomes an
עיר הנדחת, Ir Nidachas, would endanger the rest of the land, the
rest of the country.
יושבי עירם, Yoshvei Iram, they seduced,
enticed the dwellers of their city, ולא יושבי עיר אחרת, v'lo yoshvei
ir acheres, not of another city. So that means the מדיחים madichim
have to be מתוכה. mitocheha. The one seducing the city to idolatry
have to be from the city itself.
לאמר, Lemor, to say, שצריכים עדים והתראה, she-tzrichim eidim v'hasra'ah, that you
need to give have witnesses and warning. Now where do you get
that from, the word לאמר? lemor? So רש"י Rashi says that the
end of the פסוק pasuk where
it says לאמר נלכה ונעבדה, lemor nelcha v'na'avdah, let us go worship
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So if you have to be able to
report what they said, it must be with עדים. eidim. And if
you have
עדים eidim then there must be התראה. hasra'ah. I actually think it
has more to do with the word לאמר, lemor, to say, indicating
that there is a התראה, hasra'ah, there is warning that is being
given.
That is because we've learned before in cases of
מסית ומדיח, maseis u-madiach, some people that you're מכמינים עדים, machmin eidim,
you hide
witnesses. Here for somebody who's trying to seduce an individual for עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. But here to make it an עיר הנדחת, Ir
Nidachas, you have to actually have
עדים והתראה. eidim v'hasra'ah. לאמר, Lemor, לכל אחד ואחד, l'chol echad v'echad,
for every individual who worships עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah until you get
to the majority of the city and then it becomes, the whole
city becomes an עיר הנדחת. Ir Nidachas.
Okay, אתמר, itmar, it was taught. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
חולקין עיר אחת לשני שבטים. chokin ir achas l'shnei shevatim. It's possible
that one city is divided between two different tribes just in general
in the land of Israel. ריש לקיש אמר, Reish Lakish amar, אין
חולקין ein chokin עיר אחת לבי שבטים, ir achas l'bei shevatim, you
do not divide it.
Now the problem of course is that there's the general approach of
the גמרא Gemara is that ירושלים Yerushalayim was divided between יהודה Yehudah
and בנימין, Binyamin, but that could be like just an exception, but
other than ירושלים Yerushalayim at least ריש לקיש'ס Reish Lakish's claim is
that you did not divide a city between two tribes. איתיבי Eiseiv
רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
challenged ריש לקיש Reish Lakish from our משנה. Mishnah. עד שיהיו מדיחיה
מתוכה ומאותו שבט. Ad she-yihyu madicheha mitocheha u-me'oso shevet. The seducers have
to be from the city and from the same tribe. So מאי
לאו, mai lav, אף על גב af al gav דמדיחיה מתוך העיר,
d'madicheha mitoch ha-ir, אי איכא מאותו שבט אין ואי לא לא. ee
ika me'oso shevet in v'ee lo lo. So how do you have,
what does it mean by making a second criteria? It means that
it's possible that you can have the seducers, the enticers from within
the city, but that they could be from a different tribe. How
would you get them both to be from within the city and
from a different tribe? It must be that there could be two
tribes for a city. So let's say the northern part of the
city is ראובן Reuven and the southern part of the city is
שמעון. Shimon. So if the ראובן Reuven came and seduced and enticed
all of the שמעון Shimon members of the city to worship עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, and that was the majority of the city, it
would not be an עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas because the enticer was
not from the same city as those who actually worshipped עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. So there you see that you can have one city
divided between two tribes. שמע מינה Shma mina חולקין לבי שבטים. chokin
l'bei shevatim. So the גמרא Gemara
says לא, lo, דנפלה ליה בירושה. d'naflah leh biy'rushah. No, it could
be that the whole city is ראובן. Reuven. How do you have
somebody from שמעון Shimon that's enticing the rest of the city and
he is a member of that city? Oh well his, you know.
He inherited it from his mother and that and his father is
from שמעון, Shimon, but his mother was from ראובן Reuven and he
inherited it from his mother. That's how you could have somebody in
the same city from a different tribe. אי נמי, Ei nami, or
even a simpler answer, אי נמי יהבו
ניהליה במתנה. Ei nami yehavu neihalei bematana. I don't know why I
said it was sold, but anyway, somebody gifted him the land or
sold him the land. So it's very possible that as a city
the city is totally within one tribe's territory but a particular individual
could be a city dweller and nevertheless be of a different tribe.
איתיבי. Eitivei. Okay, so now we're going still try to, now that
we quoted the debate, we're going to try to see if there's
other ways we can prove it. ערים תשע מאת שני השבטים האלו.
Arim tesha mei'et shnei hashevatim ha'eilu. Nine cities were given from these
two tribes, יהודה Yehuda and שמעון, Shimon, for the, for the לויים
Levi'im cities. Okay, so מאי לאו? mai lav? So that's a פסוק
pasuk in יהושע. Yehoshua. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו ארבעה
פלגא מהאי וארבעה פלגא מהאי? mai lav arba palga mehai ve'arba palga
mehai? It must mean four and a half were given from יהודה
Yehuda and four and a half were given from שמעון. Shimon. One
city was shared between them. ושמע מינה חולקין עיר אחת לשני שבטים.
Ushma mina cholkin ir achat lishnei shevatim. And you see that you
can divide one city to two tribes.
הגמרא Hagemara says לא ארבעה מהאי וחמשה מהאי. lo arba mehai vechamisha
mehai. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, it just means nine between them both.
One gave four, one gave five. How do you prove from that
that one city was divided? So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
לפרושי פירושי. Ei hachi liprushei peirushei. If that's true, why didn't it
say יהודה Yehuda gave four, שמעון Shimon gave five? The fact that
it says between the two of them they gave nine suggests that
there was at least one city that was held by both of
them. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Okay, it's difficult, but
it doesn't absolutely prove it. All right, so that's the end of
that discussion. Back to עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat. Top of דף קיב
עמוד א. daf kuf yud beis amud aleph. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu.
They raised the question. שהודחו מאליהן מהו? shehudchu mei'aleihen mahu? Let's say
the city did not require any enticers. Everybody just themselves just decided
to be עובד עבודה זרה. oved avoda zara. Nobody was enticing anyone
else. Okay. וידיחו
אמר רחמנא ולא שהודחו מאליהן. Vayidichu amar rachmana velo shehudchu mei'aleihen. Does
it have to be that there were people that pushed them off
the path that enticed them, and not that they did it to
themselves? או דילמא אפילו הודחו מאליהן? O dilma afilu hudchu mei'aleihen? Or
do we say no
even if they did it themselves, maybe that's even worse, they're ממש
רשעים. mamash resha'im. It's not just that they were swept up by
other people's persuasiveness. So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta shema,
let's come and see if we can prove it from our משנה.
Mishna. הדיחוה נשים וקטנים. hidichua nashim uktanimm. If women or children are
the enticers, then it is not an עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, why is that? להוי כהודחו מאליהן.
lehavei kehudchu mei'aleihen. Let it be like just that they did on
their own. Meaning if there's a requirement that needs to be enticers,
so you could say, okay, who constitutes? It has to be two,
it has to be men. But if the point is is that
even without enticers if they just did it on their own they
could be considered עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, so if the women and
children are not, don't constitute
enticers for this הלכה, halacha, let it just be like they, the
city acted on its own. How could women and children be worse
than just doing it on your own if there's no real requirement
of having somebody who constitutes an enticer? And the גמרא Gemara says
yeah, it could be worse. Why?
הנך בתר נפשייהו גרירי. Hanech batar nafshaihu griri. Those when you're just
doing it on their own, they're going because of their own decision,
their own desire to do it. So they're really serious about the
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. But הנך בתר נשים וקטנים גרירי, hanech batar
nashim uktanimm griri, but in the case about women and children they're
just being persuaded by these women and children, so maybe it's easier
for them to reverse themselves and change course, and therefore maybe it's
not as bad. It sort of suggests the idea that
people will really be committed to it and serious about it if
they're doing it themselves, or if they're following men, certainly shows biases
in terms of patriarchy and male leadership or whatever, then they're really
going to commit to it. But if it was just women or
children, maybe at some point people can just be dismissive, ah, just
a woman, just a child, shouldn't listen to them, maybe they'll reverse
themselves, maybe they're not as deeply committed to it. So maybe that
actually is worse than the other two cases. Obviously reflects a lot
of societal assumptions here. Okay. עד שיודח רובה. Ad sheyudach rubah. Of
course for it to be a whole city, it has to be
the majority of the city worships עבודה זרה. avoda zara. היכי עבדינן?
Heichi avdinan? And the גמרא Gemara says how are we going to
figure it out? Because we have to decide whether this is a
case of individuals or the majority, but you're not going to know
until you process everyone. So how are we going to figure this
out? אמר רב יהודה דנין וחובשין דנין וחובשין. Amar רב יהודה danin
vechovshin danin vechovshin. So you judge somebody, oh, you worshiped עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, you're חייב סקילה, chayav sekila, and you put them in
jail. Next person, worshiped עבודה זרה, avoda zara, חייב סקילה, chayav sekila,
put them in jail, and you keep on waiting until you see
what the numbers are. And if the numbers at the end equal
the majority, then you decide, okay, עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, you don't
get סקילה, sekila, you're going to get סייף. sayif. and הרג. hereg.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה עולא, amar lei Ulla, עולא
Ulla said, no, you can't do that, משום דמיענשינן דינן של אלו.
mishum d'me'ansinan dinan shel elu. You are oppressing their judgment. Once somebody
has been given the judgment that they're going to be executed, you
have to do it immediately, otherwise it's considered עינוי הדין. innui ha-din.
So you can't actually pass judgment on them and then not act
on it. So אלא אמר עולא, ela amar Ulla, דנים וסוקלים דנים
וסוקלים. danim v'soklim danim v'soklim. No, you work as long as you're
seeing individuals, you keep on passing judgment, giving סקילה, sekilah, passing judgment,
giving סקילה, sekilah, because right now each individual is just an individual,
but you're keeping tally, and once you get to the person that's
going to now make it the majority of the city, then you
realize oh, we have an עיר הנידחת ir nidachas on our hands,
and from this point on everybody gets הרג hereg and not סקילה
sekilah and you're going to burn everything in the city. Okay, ריש
לקיש, Resh Lakish, that's what רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says. ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish אמר מרבין להם בתי דינים. amar marbin lahem batei dinim.
Well no, we try to actually process it all in one day.
We don't want to give people סקילה sekilah and in the end
it's going to be an עיר הנידחת. ir nidachas. We don't want
to be מענה את הדין. me'aneh es hadin. So what you do
is you just have many many many many בתי דינים, batei dinim,
you have like you know a thousand בתי דינים, batei dinim, you
know, no wait, gets to see everybody right away and therefore you're
able to decide on the day itself whether it's one or the
other. רש''י Rashi points out it's not because you're not allowed to
judge two דיני נפשות dinei nefashos on the same day, you are
allowed if it's the same case, it's the same like you know
thing, but it's... but here it's just got to process everyone. Okay,
so that's how ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says you would deal with
it. So איני? eini? The גמרא Gemara says is that really possible
what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is suggesting? דאמר רבי חמא בר יוסי
d'amar Rabi Chama bar Yossi אמר רבי אושעיא amar Rabi Oshaya והוצאת
את האיש ההוא או את האשה ההיא v'hotzeisa es ha'ish hahu o
es ha'isha hahi you should take that man or that woman to
your gate and you should stone them by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
איש ואשה אתה מוציא לשעריך ish v'isha atah motzi l'sharecha a man
or woman you take to your gate, meaning the judgment is in
that city itself. ואי אתה מוציא כל העיר כולה לשערך, v'ei atah
motzi kol ha'ir kulo l'sharecha, but if it's an entire city it
cannot be judged by the judges of the city, it has to
be judged by the central, you know, the national בית דין, beis
din, it has to be judged by the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So now we got a problem. You can't
say we're going process everybody and make it into an עיר הנידחת,
ir nidachas,
because the making of an עיר הנידחת ir nidachas has to be
decided by the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. And presumably it's also the problem of...
I mean it's not clear that this is a challenge on רבי
יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, but it seems like it could be as well,
that if you're giving every individual סקילה sekilah as they're coming through
your doors, then ultimately when the... and then you say oh look
we got a majority, let's refer it to the סנהדרין הגדולה, Sanhedrin
haGedolah, but then the סנהדרין הגדולה Sanhedrin haGedolah hasn't really been involved
in the whole process
of seeing all the people that were עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah
zarah, the whole process of determining that it's an עיר הנידחת, ir
nidachas, they're only like coming in in the middle after the local
בית דין beis din essentially established all those facts. So how are
we going to get it that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin is going to
be involved and to... while we're trying to figure out is it
an עיר הנידחת ir nidachas or is it just a case of
individuals. So the גמרא Gemara says let's see how the גמרא Gemara
answers it.
אלא מרבין להם בתי דינים, ela marbin lahem batei dinim, we like
ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish idea that you have a lot of בתי
דינים batei dinim to process this all quickly, ומעיינין בדיניהם u'me'aynin b'dineihem
and you investigate the case but you don't actually have the גמר
דין, gmar din, because if you actually had the גמר דין gmar
din you wouldn't be able to postpone it and you'd have to
give them סקילה, sekilah, right, like all we said before, and you
don't want... and we need to get the בית דין הגדול Beis
Din haGadol involved if it's going to be ultimately a case of
an עיר הנידחת. ir nidachas. So you sort of establish all the
facts but you don't come yet to any conclusion. ומסקינן להו לבית
דין הגדול u'maskinan lehu l'Beis Din haGadol
and once you see that you have like a majority, then it's
like oh okay let's bring all this whole case to the בית
דין הגדול Beis Din haGadol and then the בית דין הגדול, Beis
Din haGadol, there's no עינוי דין innui din because nothing's been complete
yet, בית דין הגדול Beis Din haGadol gets involved and we know
it's going to be an עיר הנידחת ir nidachas case and now
they're going to process all of the cases. וגמירי להו לדייני לדינייהו
v'gmiri lehu l'dayanei l'dineihu and there the בית דין הגדול Beis Din
haGadol they finish the גמר דין gmar din וקטלי להו v'katli lehu
and they killed them. Okay, הכה תכה את יושבי העיר hakeh sakeh
es yoshvei ha'ir so now smite those who dwelt in the city,
the משנה mishnah said that even a passing camel driver or donkey
driver is included in the members of the city to determine whether
the majority goes one way or the other, but it did not
give any exact criteria and that's going to be here. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught,
החמר והגמל hachamar v'hagamal the donkey driver or the camel driver עובר
ממקום למקום over mimakom l'makom passing through from place to place, לן
בתוכה ונהדחו עמה lan b'sochah v'nehidchu imah and they slept over in
the city and they were then went ahead and they worshipped עבודה
זרה avodah zarah with the city.
אם נשתהו שם שלשים יום, im nishtahu sham shloshim yom, if they're
there 30 days then they are considered to be יושבי העיר ההיא,
yoshvei ha'ir hahi, dwellers of that city and therefore they make the
city an עיר הנידחת ir nidachas if you needed their... you know,
their numbers to make it a majority, and that would be the
הלכה, halachah, they would get killed by the sword and their money
would be destroyed.
פחות מכאן, pachas mikan, so let's say they were less than 30
days, so now if you... you can't count them with the numbers
of the city, so now you don't have the majority of the
city worshipping עבודה זרה avoda zara, *Avoda Zara*. So if that's true,
הן בסקילה וממונם פלט *hen b'skila u'mamonam palat*, so then they would
get stoned. Actually, I was saying that it would determine the fate
of the city, which is also true, but there's another point to
it as well. Even if the whole city is the majority, are
they part of the city that gets—they could still be just passers-by.
So the whole city, we could have ninety percent of the city
worship עבודה זרה avoda zara. *Avoda Zara*, it's all going to be
an עיר נדחת ir nidachas *Ir Nidachat*, חרב *cherev*, the whole thing.
These people, this donkey driver that worshipped עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, is
he worshipping עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara* as a member of the city?
And then he gets the sword and his money gets destroyed. Or
is he worshipping it as a just as a visitor? And then
he'll get—it'll be בסקילה *b'skila* and his money won't get destroyed. It
says, depends if he dwelled there for thirty days. So once you
dwell there for thirty days, you're counted amongst the dwellers of the
city. That's relevant to determining how you decide whether the majority's on
this side or that side, if you need those numbers for the
majority, and it's also relevant to determining whether you get some of
the same fate as the people of the city or an independent
fate. Okay, so that is the שיעור *shiur*, thirty days. So now
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this: רמיניה *Remini*, I'll ask you
on this: כמה יהא בעיר ויהא כאנשי העיר *Kama yehei ba'ir v'yehei
k'anshei ha'ir*? We have a teaching in בבא בתרא *Bava Batra*, how
long do you have to be dwelling in the city to be
considered like a citizen, a member of the city, in order to
be paying the taxes for communal protection,
communal defenses, sort of local civic needs?
So it says, י"ב חודש *Yud-Bet Chodesh*, twelve months. So what is
it? Is it thirty days or is it twelve months? So אמר
רבא Amar Rava: *Amar Rava*, says רבא *Rava*, לא קשיא *lo kashya*.
הא למהוי מבני מתא, הא למהוי מיתבי מתא *Ha l'mehavi mibnei mata,
ha l'mehavi miyatvei mata*. There's a difference to say you're a member
of the city or you're a dweller in the city. Okay? So
once you've taken up residence thirty days, you are a dweller in
the city. But you're not yet like a citizen, you're not a
member of the city until you've been there for a full year.
And to pay for the city's taxes and defenses and infrastructure, that's
only when you're a member of the city. But to be a
dweller in the city, that has relevance for עיר נדחת *Ir Nidachat*
and maybe possibly other things as well as we're about to see.
Interesting question about the criteria of מדיחיה מתוכה *midecheha mitocha*, that also
the enticers have to be from the city itself. Do the enticers
have to be from the יושבי העיר *yoshvei ha'ir* or do they
have to be from the בני העיר *bnei ha'ir*? Not clear. Okay,
ותניא *v'tanya*, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says and we see this distinction
in the following ברייתא Baraisa *Baraita*. תניא *Tanya* is often a challenge,
but like ninety-five percent of the time, but sometimes it's actually quoted
as a supporting text. We taught in the ברייתא braisa *Baraita*: המודר
הנאה מבני העיר *Hamudar hana'ah mibnei ha'ir*, somebody who vows that he
will not receive benefit from the members of the city: אם נשתהא
שם י"ב חודש אסור ליהנות ממנו, פחות מכאן מותר ליהנות ממנו *Im
nishtaha sham Yud-Bet Chodesh assur l'hanot mimenu, pachot mikan mutar l'hanot mimenu*.
So if it's within twelve—if somebody's there twelve months, he's considered now
a member of the city, and that person is included in your
vow and you can't derive benefit, less than that you can. However,
if you did not say בני העיר *bnei ha'ir*, but if you
said ביושבי העיר *b'yoshvei ha'ir*, that you won't get הנאה *hana'ah* from
those who dwell in the city: אם נשתהא ל' יום אסור ליהנות
ממנו, פחות מכאן מותר ליהנות ממנו *Im nishtaha lamed yom assur l'hanot
mimenu, pachot mikan mutar l'hanot mimenu*. Then it goes by thirty days,
not by twelve months. Exactly the distinction that we have been arguing
for. Okay. החרם אותה ואת כל אשר בה *Hacharem otah v'et kol
asher bah*. So that's to determine: is it an עיר נדחת *Ir
Nidachat*? Now we get to the punishment: destroy it, put it all
under the ban and everything that is in it. תנו רבנן Tano
Rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*: החרם אותה ואת כל אשר בה *Hacharem otah v'et
kol asher bah*, so פרט לנכסי צדיקים tzaddikim שבחוצה לה *prat l'nichsei
tzadikim shebechutzah lah*. Everything that is in it you destroy, but property
that is owned by the non-sinners, by the non-violators, that is not
physically in the city, that you would not destroy. Okay, fine. Now
how about those that actually were עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei avodah zarah?
*ovdei avoda zara*? Why don't we maybe should limit also that to
כל אשר בה *kol asher bah*? Maybe if they have property outside
the city, it won't be included. So we're going to include it.
ואת כל אשר בה *V'et kol asher bah* לרבות נכסי צדיקים tzaddikim
שבתוכה *l'rabot nichsei
tzadikim shebetochah*. So, you know, אותה *otah* seems like it was החרם
אותה *hacharem otah*, only it, not the stuff outside of it. But
so that excludes the property of the צדיקים *tzadikim* that's not in
the city, that's only אותה *otah*, the city itself. ואת כל אשר
בה *v'et kol asher bah*, but everything in it means, I'm sorry,
even though you didn't worship עבודה זרה *avoda zara*, if it's in
the city, it's going to get destroyed. לרבות נכסי צדיקים שבתוכה *l'rabot
nichsei tzadikim shebetochah*. שללה shlalah. *Shlalah*, its
booty, its property, ולא שלל שמים shlal shamayim, *v'lo shlal shamayim*, not
that belonging to heaven, things that are הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*, that was
mentioned in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, we'll get to that momentarily. ואת
כל שללה shlalah. תקבוץ אל תוך רחובה *V'et kol shlalah tikbotz el
toch rechovah*, all of its property of its wealth you should gather
to the road, לרבות נכסי רשעים resha'im שבחוצה לה *l'rabot nichsei reshaim
shebechutzah lah*. So then This includes the property of those who worship
the עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* even if it's not in the city.
How do you get that from וכל שללה shlala *vechol shelalah*? Because
there's a difference. Before it says כל אשר בה *kol asher ba*,
everything in it, it has to physically be in it. וכל שללה
*vechol shelalah*, all of its property, its wealth, doesn't say it has
to be physically situated in it. The wealth that is owned by
the property owned by the members of the city is the שלל
*shalal* of the city even if it is never in the city,
not in the city itself. Okay, so that's what we learn out
from שללה *shelalah*. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* actually says that it has
to have been in the city at one time and is now
out of the city. Okay, which makes even more sense. It says
property of the city, but it's not אשר בה *asher ba*, but
it is of the city, it is שלל *shalal*. So the way
we sort of strike the balance of those two is to distinguish
between צדיקים *tzadikim* and רשעים reshaim *reshaim*. צדיקים *tzadikim* it's only אשר
בה *asher ba*, רשעים reshaim *reshaim* it's כל שללה *kol shelalah* even
outside of it. Where were we? ואת כל שללה תקבוץ *ve'et kol
shlalah tikpotz* שבחוצה לה *shebechutza lah*. אמר רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda,
*Amar Rav Chisda*: ובנקבצים בתוכה besochah *u'venikpatzim betocha*. It says תקבוץ אל
תוך רחובה *tikpotz el toch rechovah*, gather, so only things that can
be gathered into the, you know, into it. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
means like within the day. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda: *Amar
Rav Chisda*: so it's also considered to be still accessible by the
city. Okay, so and again רש"י Rashi *Rashi* also adds the criteria
that it was once in the city. So something that's very far
away stops being considered שללה *shlalah*. It's not geographically close, it was
never there before and so on, or it was never there before.
Okay.
Where are we? אמר רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Amar Rabbi Shimon*: Did
I skip a line? לא לשמים *lo l'shemayim* ואת כל *ve'et kol*
oh yeah, I think I skipped down a line. ואת כל שללה
*ve'et kol shlalah* לרבות נכסי רשעים שבחוצה לה *lerabbot nichsei reshaim shebechutza
lah*. אמר רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Amar Rabbi Shimon*: מפני מה *mipnei
mah* I'm sorry, I skipped down a line far. אמר רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Amar Rabbi Shimon*: מפני מה אמרה תורה נכסי צדיקים שבתוכה
יאבדו *mipnei mah amrah Torah nichsei tzadikim shebetocha yovdu*? Why does the
property of the righteous inside of it get destroyed? מגרם להם שידורו
בתוכה *migram lahem sheyeduru betocha*? What made, you know, people that were
not wicked dwell in this city that turned out to be all
these evildoers? ממונם *mammonam*. It must have been for financial reasons, certainly
it wasn't for social reasons or for religious reasons. So ועל כן
ממונם אבד *ve'al ken mammonam avad*. They are going to sacrifice their
money since they should not that is what led them to dwell
in this city with רשעים *reshaim*. Now going back to what I
jumped ahead before. אמר מר Amar mar *Amar mar*: ואת כל שללה
תקבוץ לרבות נכסי רשעים שבחוצה לה *ve'et kol shlalah tikpotz lerabbot nichsei
reshaim shebechutza lah*. אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*: ובנקבצים בתוכה *u'venikpatzim
betocha*. That when we include the that of the of the רשעים
*reshaim* that's not in the city, it has to be stuff that
can be gathered in and again as רש"י *Rashi* says within the
day. אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*: פקדונות של אנשי עיר הנדחת
Ir Nidachas מותרים *pikdonot shel anshei ir hanidachat muttarim*. If you have
things that have been, you know, things given to be entrusted to
others of the עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas, *ir hanidachat*, that's permissible. So
it's very unclear who is the entruster, who is the entrustee. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. היכי דמי Heichi dami,
*Heichi dami*? What's the case? אילימא Ilima דעיר אחרת ואינהו גבה *Ileima
de'ir acheret ve'inhu gabah*? פשיטא דמותרים *Peshita de'muttarim*. If it belongs to
members of a different city and just people in the עיר הנדחת
Ir Nidachas, *ir hanidachat* are watching over property of people of a
different city. So obviously it's permissible. Now I know why it's obviously
permissible, it's still included in ואת כל אשר בה *ve'et kol asher
ba*, it is physically in the city, but, you know, again, it's
certainly not in any way if it included in the words שללה
*shelalah*. It doesn't belong to this city at all and therefore it
seems to obviously be excluded. Okay.
So פשיטא דמותרים *peshita de'muttarim*. לאו שללה הוא *Lav shlalah hu*. It's
not its שללה *shlalah*, it might be בתוכה *betocha* but it's not
its שללה *shlalah*, it's not שייך *shayach* to the city. ואלא דדידהו
*Ve'ela de'didhu*, it must be that it's property of the city, of
the עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas *ir hanidachat*, ואינהו בעיר אחרת *ve'inhu be'ir
acheret*, and it's being watched on their behalf in some other
city. Okay, somebody in this city entrusted his cow to somebody in
a different city. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, well then, you
know, what do you mean that it's not, you don't destroy it?
It should go by what we just said before. אי דנקבצים בתוכה
*I de'nikpatzim betocha*, if it could be gathered in, so אמאי מותרים
*amai muttarim*? Then why is it permitted? That's כל שללה *kol shlalah*,
should be, you know, as what we said, it includes even stuff
that's outside. ואי אין נקבצים בתוכה *Ve'ee ein nikpatzim betocha*, and if
it can't be gathered in, it's very far away, הא אמר חדא
זימנא *ha amar chada zimna*, you already said that if it couldn't
be gathered in. So we already, so what is the need to
tell us that something that is being watched and guarded is not
destroyed?
If it's, if it's being watched in, if it's from outside of
the city it's obvious, if it's from within the city, it's not
that type of a categorical statement, it goes by whether it could
be gathered or not. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: לעולם דעיר
אחרת דאפקדי בתוכה *le'olam de'ir acheret depikdi betocha*. No, no, no, we're
talking that it is from another city and it was entrusted in
this city. And you say oh it's obvious, you know, that because
it's not שללה *shlalah*, it's not connected to this city at all.
So here's why it's not so obvious. והכא במאי עסקינן Bimai askinan,
*Ve'hacha demai askinan*, what are we talking about? דקביל עליה אחריות *Dekabbil
aleih achrayut*, that the person watching it who's in the city takes
responsibility for it. עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas accepted, you know, liability for
it if anything were to happen to it. מהו דתימא כיון דקביל
עליה אחריות כדידיה דמי, mahu d'teima kivan d'kibbel alei achrayus kididei dami,
since he's accepting liability, there's going to be real consequence to him
if it gets lost. So to some degree this is considered like
his property and that actually is a principle we have, for example,
by חמץ בפסח chametz b'Pesach that if you've accepted liability, it's considered
to be like your חמץ chametz and you transgress. And we're going
to see something also similar about that when it comes to קרבנות
korbanos when we turn the page. So that, I might have thought
is enough to make it like yours, and that would put it
in the category of שללה. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that
it's not. So that actually is really a חידוש. chiddush. Even though
it's בתוכה and even though the people in the city have responsibility
for it, it is still not in the category of שללה.
Okay, next point. אמר רב חסדא, בהמה
חציה של עיר הנדחת וחציה של עיר אחרת.
behema chetzyah shel
Ir Nidachas v'chetzyah shel ir acheres. Let's say you have an animal
that's of an עיר הנדחת Ir Nidachas? but it's half owned by
this city and half owned of another city.
So what's the הלכה? halachah? אסורה. asurah. You, it's all forbidden. Once
the הלכה halachah gets passed that this is an עיר הנדחת, Ir
Nidachas. it applies to this animal. This animal is a non-divisible unit,
so the whole animal becomes forbidden. עיסה
חציה של עיר הנדחת וחציה של עיר אחרת. isah chetzyah shel Ir
Nidachas v'chetzyah shel ir acheres. However, if you have some dough, you
know,
some inanimate object, something that's easily divided and it's half owned by
this, somebody in this city and half owned by another city. Even
after the city gets determined to be an עיר הנדחת, Ir Nidachas
the הלכה halachah is מותרת. mutteres. It's permissible, meaning you divide it
and the part that belongs to the, and you give the half
to whoever is in the other city, and then it is permissible.
Okay? Because there you say the whole status of עיר הנדחת ir
nidachas only applies to half of the dough. And somehow you're allowed
to divide it and decide which half is which. Okay? Something that
was in a state of being easily divisible and was not seen
as one integral, undivided unit. So that type of a thing, only
half of it became forbidden. Okay,
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? בהמה כמאן דלא פליגא דמיא.
behema k'man d'lo pliga damya.
The animal cannot be seen as divided. It's one integral unit. So
since the status of עיר הנדחת ir nidachas applies to part of
it, it applies to all of it. But עיסה כמאן דפליגא דמיא.
isah k'man d'pliga damya. But dough is easily divided and therefore the
status only applies to half of it. בעי רב חסדא. ba'ei Rav
Chisda. Rav Chisda asked: בהמת עיר הנדחת מהו דתהני בה שחיטה לטהרה
מידי נבלה? behemas Ir Nidachas mahu d'tehani bah shechitah l'taharah midei neveilah?
What happens if you שחט shacht an animal from an עיר הנדחת?
ir nidachas. So you can't eat it, it's אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah.
But does it have טומאת נבלה? tumas neveilah? If an animal died
by itself, it's a נבלה neveilah and it's טמא. tamei. If it
was slaughtered and it is even if it winds up being a
טרפה, treifah, you know, but once it's slaughtered, it is not a
נבלה neveilah and it is not טמא. tamei. So when you slaughter
it, even though you can't eat it because it's אסור בהנאה, assur
b'hana'ah, maybe it will, will the שחיטה shechitah help that it will
no longer be a, that it will not be considered a נבלה
neveilah like if it had died by itself? So what's the question?
לפי חרב אמר רחמנא לא שנא שחטיה ומשחט ולא שנא קטליה ומקטל.
lefi charev amar Rachmana lo shna shachtei u'mashchat v'lo shna katlei u'maktal.
It says you shall kill the animals based on the, by the
edge of the sword. So it doesn't matter how you kill them
by the edge of the sword, whether you just stab them, you
know, or cut them from behind, or you cut the neck and
you do a שחיטה. shechitah. Either way, it was a fulfillment of
לפי חרב. lefi charev. And therefore it was not considered like you
שחט shacht it. It was considered like you executed it and killed
it because of the הלכה halachah of לפי חרב. lefi charev. And
therefore it does not lose the status of נבלה. neveilah. It is
not considered to have been שחט shacht it. You could have asked
a similar question like would you transgress אותו ואת בנו לא תשחטו
ביום אחד oso v'es bno lo sishchatu b'yom echad if you שחט
shacht an animal of an עיר הנדחת. ir nidachas Is it not
considered to be a שחיטה? shechitah? לפי חרב אמר רחמנא. lefi charev
amar Rachmana.
Where were we? אמר רחמנא לא שנא שחטיה ומשחט ולא שנא קטליה
ומקטל. amar Rachmana lo shna shachtei u'mashchat v'lo shna katlei u'maktal. או
דילמא? o dilma? second wide of the widest lines. כיון דשחטיה מהניא
ליה שחיטה. kivan d'shachtei mehanya lei shechitah. No, it is still considered
a
שחיטה. shechitah. מהו? mahu? תיקו. teiku. We don't know. Okay, good question.
בעי רב יוסף. ba'ei Rav Yosef. Another question. שער נשים צדקניות מהו?
se'ar nashim tzidkaniyos mahu? What about the hair of the righteous women,
of the women that were not עובדי עבודה זרה? By the way,
fascinating question we have not discussed, right? Which is how do you
count the members of the city? Just the men or the men
and the women?
Right. So anyway, but now that does not get discussed surprisingly in
the גמרא. Gemara But when you have to destroy the property of
everybody in it, you know, everybody's property is destroyed as we've established,
that's in the city. Does that include hair on somebody's head? Now
that's pretty funny. You would think that hair on somebody's head is
not considered property, it's considered their body. You know, maybe you could
have asked it by the רשעים because if they're going to be
executed, you know, you know, maybe there we could sort of look,
begin to look at their hair as like property. Although that certainly
evokes images of the Holocaust. But anyway, so it's, but it's a
fascinating question to be asking about the נשים צדקניות. nashim tzidkaniyos. So
what is the story there?
So now let's see. And the question is why is he only
asking about the righteous? מהו? Mahu? So רצונך. retzoncha. אמר רבא: הא
דרשעים אסורה—I'm Ha dreshaim asura sorry, right, הא דרשעים אסורה—so ha dreshaim
asura your question suggests that the hair of the people that are
being executed is forbidden, which you know, like I said, could make
more sense because that's more considered to be property, they're going to
be executed.
Therefore you just want to ask about the righteous women. But one
minute, תקבץ ושרפת כתיב, Tikbotz vesarafta ksiv, it says you should gather
and burn, מי שאינו מחוסר קביצה ושרפה, Misheinno mchusar kbitza usreifa, the
only things you burn are the things that all you have to
do is gather them into the into the road. They don't require
something to make them into, you know, objects, okay? יצא זה שמחוסר
תלישה וקביצה ושרפה, Yatza ze shemchusar tlisha ukhvitza usreifa, this requires cutting
the hair and then gathering it and burning it. So even if
you were to view the hair on the heads of the wicked
that you are killing and executing as a type of a property,
it's not a property that the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת ir
nidachas applies because you would first have to shave it from from
their heads. So that's true even about those that were worshipped עבודה
זרה, then it's certainly true about those that did not worship עבודה
זרה. אלא
אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather Rava says, בפאה נכרית היכי דמי,
Bpeia nokhris heichi dami,
what, I'm sorry just skipped a line, בפאה נכרית. Bpeia nokhris. Okay,
we're talking here about a wig. That's the phrase of a wig
even in modern Hebrew. Okay, so
so that's the question: is the wig considered a natural hair wig
something that you would have to go ahead or and burn? What's
the question? היכי דמי, what's the question? אי דמחובר בגופא כגופא דמיא,
I demchubar bgufo kegufa damya, if she's wearing it attached to her
head, we would treat it like her body. What does it mean
like her body? It means, well, it could mean like her body,
but רש"י says it just means like her clothing. You know, even
though we say we destroy all the property of the צדיקים in
the city, we are taken for granted that we do not ask
them to strip naked and we do not destroy their clothing. So
if she's wearing it, it's like her clothing. Okay, if a one
of the people we are killing was wearing a wig, that's property
and we would destroy it. But if one of the women we're
not killing is wearing the wig, then it's clothing and we wouldn't
destroy clothing of the צדקניות, tzidkaniyos, which we don't destroy.
לא צריכא דתליא בסיפתא, Lo tzrikha ditalya bsifta, now what we're talking
about is that it's on a peg. She's not wearing it. So
so therefore what's the question? כנכסי צדיקים שבתוכה דמיא ואבד, Kenikhsei tzaddikim
shebtokha damya veavad, do we just treat it as like property? It's
your wig, it's a property, we're going to destroy it? או דילמא
כיון דעיילה ונפקא כלבושה דמיא, Odilma kivan daila venafka kilvusha damya, or
do we say since, you know, she takes it on and off
and she sort of like regularly wears it, we just consider it
to be like her body even when she's not wearing it? Okay,
so it would be more like her clothes than clothes. Clothes, only
the clothes she's wearing we don't destroy, but the but the wig,
you know, that's so much more part of her body that even
when she's not wearing it we would treat it as type of
her as similar to clothing that she was wearing and we would
not destroy it. That is the question whether we would say that
or not, and the answer is תיקו. teiku. Okay, ושללה לא
תקבץ אל תוך רחובה, Veshalala lo tikpotz el tokho rechovah, תנו רבנן,
Tano Rabbanan, אין לה רחוב אינה נעשית עיר הנדחת דברי רבי ישמעאל.
Ein lah rechov einah ne-asis ir nidachas divrei Rabbi Yishmael. We did
not have the opinion in the גמרא. Gemara If it doesn't have
a road, it does not become עיר הנדחת ir nidachas. because it
says gather into the road. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, and this is what our משנה Mishnah. says,
אין לה רחוב עושים לה רחוב, Ein lah rechov osim lah rechov,
if it does not have one, you make it one. במאי קמיפלגי,
Bmai kamifligi, what is the debate? מר סבר רחובה מעיקרא משמע, Mar
savar rechovah me-ikara mashma, its road meaning the road that it already
had, ומר סבר רחובה השתא נמי משמע, Umar savar rechovah hashta nami
mashma, its road could include one that we are making right now.
Doesn't exactly define what's behind that debate. Okay, top of קי"ב עמוד
ב'. kuf yud bet amud bet. Now we get to the I
would say the harder part of our משנה. Mishnah The משנה Mishnah
says that because it says שללה and not שלל שמים, shlal shamayim,
you don't destroy things that are sanctified, but it did talk about
like letting them rot and, you know, and burying them and so
on, which wasn't clear. If it's שלל שמים, shlal shamayim then why
aren't they just totally saved? So let's take a, you know, why
do you have to like let them rot? So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with
this. תנו רבנן, הקדשות שבה יפדו. Hekdeishos shebah yifdu. So our Rabbis
taught: היו בה קדשים קדשי מזבח ימותו. Hayu bah kodshim kodshei mizbe'ach
yamusu. If there was קדשים, kodshim, קדשי מזבח kodshei mizbe'ach you have
to let them die. Why is that? Whatever happened to שללה ולא
שלל שמים? shlala velo shlal shamayim? So now you are not going
ahead and killing them by the sword, but you are letting them
die, you know, putting them in a pen and letting them die.
So what is this middle state that you don't apply the punishment
of burning and and and killing by the sword, but you also
have to let the thing, you know, rot or be destroyed? So
we will see in the גמרא. Gemara קדשי בדק הבית יפדו, Kodshei
bedek habayis yifdu, if it's just property of הקדש hekdesh but it's
not a קרבן, korban, then you could just redeem it. That makes
sense. It's not included because it's שלל שמים shalal shamayim. and you
don't and therefore, you know, you go ahead and and and you
redeem it. Now, of course, the The question is so why do
you have to redeem it? So רש"י on the משנה Mishnah makes
it sound like well you can redeem it if you want to
but maybe if you want to you just take it and walk
out of the city with it because it's של שמים. shel shamayim.
But another possibility and this is the constant sort of theme that's
going on here might be look since it was in the עיר
הנדחת ir nidachas it's somehow tainted okay so so we don't want
you to walk out with it and use it in a normal
הקדש hekdesh context we want you to redeem it that might be
what's going on here. ותרומות
ירקבו U'trumos yerakevu תרומה וירקבו truma u'rtei ומעשר שני וכתבי הקודש יגנזו
u'maaser sheni u'kisvei hakodesh yignazu and מעשר שני maaser sheni and you
know scripture you bury not exactly clear why it doesn't just say
ירקבו u'rat but let rot by מעשר שני maaser sheni maybe it
means money of מעשר שני maaser sheni anyway again make up your
mind if it's של שמים shel shamayim just walk out with it
if it's not של שמים shel shamayim then destroy it normally okay.
רבי שמעון אומר בהמתה Rabbi Shimon omer behmto its animals ולא בהמת
בכור ומעשר velo behemous bechor u'maaser not that of בכור bechor and
מעשר. maaser.
שלו Shelo its שלו shelo פרט לכסף הקדש וכסף מעשר prat lekesef
hekdesh u'kesef maaser and that again excludes money of הקדש hekdesh and
money of מעשר maaser that's
not its שלו shelo and presumably that you just walk out with.
So we're back to the question of these other things which you
don't just walk out with and you have to somehow let rot
or or bury. So let's see if we can figure this out.
אמר מר so now we're going to try and unpack this. היו
בה קדשים קדשי מזבח ימותו Hayu bo kodshim kodshim mizbeach yamusu ואמאי
ימותו v'amai yamusu why do you have to let them die? ירעו
עד שיסתאבו Yeru ad she'yistavu let them graze until they get a
blemish וימכרו v'yimkaru and then you'll be able to redeem it a
קרבן korban that has a blemish you can redeem ויפלו דמיהם לנדבה
v'yipelu dmeyhem lin'davah then you'll use the proceeds and the הקדש hekdesh
money to buy another קרבן korban why do you let them die
and your that whole הקדש hekdesh is going to waste? So it
doesn't ask why you don't just walk out of the city with
it it's asking why you don't redeem it but let's see what
the answer is and maybe that can help us with our question.
So רבי יוחנן אומר זבח רשעים תועבה Rabbi Yochanan omer zevach reshaim
toevah the sacrifice of the רשעים is an abomination and therefore that
explains why you can't just go ahead and walk out of the
city with it and bring it as a קרבן. korban. This is
owned by the people that are being killed and they're רשעים and
therefore it's invalid as a קרבן. korban. Now what would be if
it was owned by the צדיקים maybe the הלכה halacha would be
different but that is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying is
that's why even if it does not have a הלכה halacha that
you have to destroy it because it's של שמים shel shamayim you
can't sacrifice it because it would be a קרבן korban of a
רשע. rasha. And that's presumably and what he's also saying is that's
why you can't redeem it because presumably that status would transfer even
to the money
that you would redeem it on. Okay so that's the problem and
that's also why you can't redeem it. ריש לקיש אמר ממון בעלים
הוא Reish Lakish amar mamon ba'alim hu and here now it's because
this type of a קרבן korban is actually considered to be not
של שמים shel shamayim it's considered to be the property of the
owner and the הלכה halacha really is that it does fall under
the הלכה halacha that it should be destroyed with the עיר הנדחת.
ir nidachas? Okay and here in the קדשים kodshim והכא בקדשים שחייב
באחריותו v'hacha be'kodshim shechayav be'achrayuso and we're talking about קדשים kodshim that
you are liable if they get lost so it would basically somebody
said הרי עלי harey alai you take personal responsibility to bring a
קרבן korban and then you separate an animal as a קרבן korban
and if that animal gets lost then you are responsible to replace
it and once you have responsibility for it like we said on
the עמוד א' amud aleph רבי שמעון היא דאמר ממון בעלים הוא
Rabbi Shimon hi d'amar mamon ba'alim hu and it's רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon. that says that a קרבן korban that you are responsible for
it's considered to be like your property so since it is your
property you would actually it would be destroyed like the עיר הנדחת
ir nidachas, but because it's קדשים kodshim we'll take an easier hand
on it and we'll just let it die we won't actively destroy
it. So right here in this debate you have two possibilities of
how to deal with these middle cases in the משנה Mishnah and
the ברייתא of הקדש hekdesh where you don't destroy it but you
don't also walk out of the city with it. One is the
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan approach and this plays out by other things
as well which is it really is fully exempt from the הלכה
halacha of עיר הנדחת ir nidachas. but there's some reason why we
don't let you use it in its normal way. So by the
case of the קרבן korban because it's זבח רשעים zevach reshaim and
that's also why you can't redeem it but it's totally escaped from
עיר הנדחת. ir nidachas. The other approach is the ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish approach which is it really has the הלכה halacha of an
עיר הנדחת ir nidachas. okay it's it's ממון בעלים mamon ba'alim but
because it's הקדש hekdesh. we're going to more bury it or let
it rot or do something else let it die we're not going
to directly destroy it. Okay so now let's see work within ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. So the גמרא Gemara says הא מדסיפא רבי שמעון
היא רישא לאו רבי שמעון ha mid'seifa Rabbi Shimon hi reisha lav
Rabbi Shimon no you can't say it's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
it's considered yours because you're חייב אחריות chayav achrayus because the end
of the משנה Mishna has רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon making a statement
about a בהמתה behemta בהמתה ולא בהמת בכור ומעשר behemto velo behemous
bechor u'maaser so clearly the original opinion that spoke about the קדשי
מזבח kodshei mizbeach was not רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon So the גמרא
Gemara, says fine, you're right. מדסיפא ר' שמעון היא רישא לאו ר'
שמעון. mi-de-seifa Reb Shimon hi reisha lav Reb Shimon. But קדשים קלים
אליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי, kodshim kalim aliba d'Rebi Yosi HaGlili, fine. We'll
get it to be considered ממון בעלים mammon be'alim from a different
direction. Not because you're חייב באחריות, chayiv beachrayus, but it's קדשים קלים.
kodshim kalim. קדשים קלים kodshim kalim are like שלמים shlamim that the
owners can eat in all ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And that type of a
thing is considered fundamentally the property of the owners. As opposed to
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim, which according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rebi Yosi
HaGlili, well רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebi Yosi HaGlili says that קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim his חידוש chiddush is they are like the owners, but
he would concede that קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim that's fundamentally belongs to
God. Okay, and if the כהנים Kohanim are eating it, they're eating
it off of God's table. That's like קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodshim. Okay,
but קדשים קלים kodshim kalim which are eaten by the owners, not
by the כהנים, Kohanim, that's fundamentally belongs to the owners. דאמר קסבר
אליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר קדשים קלים ממון בעלים הוא. d'amar kasavar
aliba d'Rebi Yosi HaGlili d'amar kodshim kalim mammon be'alim hu. Okay, so
we're back to the same point. It is even though it's a
קרבן, korban, it's considered to belong to the owner and the הלכה
halacha really is you do destroy it, but we're just going to
do it more indirectly. And that's why also you can't redeem it
because it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it's supposed to be destroyed. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אבל קדשי קדשים מאי? aval kodshei kodshim
mai? So what would you say though if it was קדשי קדשים?
kodshei kodshim? It really was של שמים. shel shamayim. Then you would
agree יפדו, yipadu, that you could redeem it after it got a
blemish, right? Because that really would be excluded from the הלכה. halacha.
If that's true, אדקתני סיפא קדשי בדק הבית יפדו, ad de-tani seifa
kodshei bedek habayis yipadu, if the second part of the ברייתא says
you redeem things that are owned by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and not קרבנות, korbanos, so why did it have to go to
something totally different, קדשי בדק הבית? kodshei bedek habayis? According to you,
ליפלוג וליתני בדידיה, liflog ve-lisani bedidi, you could have made a distinction
within the very category of קדשי מזבח. kodshei mizbayach. במה דברים אמורים,
bameh devarim amurim, קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. What type of קרבנות korbanos
you have to let die and destroy because they're considered to belong
to the owner and they really have the הלכה halacha of עיר
הנדחת? ir nidachas That's קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. אבל קדשי קדשים, aval
kodshei kodshim, but קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim which would be considered
ממון גבוה mammon gavo'ah and של שמים, shel shamayim, that would be
יפדו, yipadu, that should be redeemed. So why didn't it make that
distinction within קרבנות korbanos if that distinction really holds? Why did it
run to the case of בדק הבית? bedek habayis? So the גמרא
Gemara says here's why. כיון דאיכא חטאת שמתו בעליה דלמיתה אזלא, keivan
de-ika chatas she-mesu be'aleha de-le-misa azla, because there is one type of
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim that you could not redeem. And what would
that be? A חטאת. chatas. The owners are going to be executed,
so it would have the
status of a חטאת שמתו בעליה. chatas she-mesu be'aleha. And the הלכה
halacha is a חטאת שמתו בעליה, chatas she-mesu be'aleha, what's the הלכה?
halacha? That you actually have to let die. That you cannot redeem
even if it gets a blemish. So once that's true, לא פסיקא
ליה, lo pesika lei, it could not just deal with it categorically.
So again, how does this משנה Mishna? read? For ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, it reads, if you have קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, they're considered
the owners, הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat. you have to
destroy it, but we're going to let it just die because it's
קדשים kodshim we'll treat it nicely. But if it was a קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodshim, then just walk out with it, okay? I don't
know, maybe he would agree זבח רשע תועבה zevach rasha to'eva so
you have to redeem it, but it certainly you can walk out
with it. Okay. And if it's a חטאת chatas and the owners
are being executed, that you would also have to let die because
חטאת שמתה. chatas she-mesa. But if it's
קדשי בדק הבית, kodshei bedek habayis, that you could just redeem and
you're totally fine and that you do not have to destroy. Again,
not exactly clear why you're redeeming it, but at least that is
totally escapes the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat. Okay. So
now the גמרא says like this. בשלמא רבי יוחנן לא אמר כריש
לקיש, bishlama Rebi Yochanan lo amar ke-Reish Lakish, we get why רבי
יוחנן Rebi Yochanan did not say like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Because
again, remember, what did רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan say? He said קדשים
kodshim is not fundamentally הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat קדשים
kodshim are exempt, but we just aren't going to be
מקריב makriv it because you know, and redeem it because it's זבח
רשע. zevach rasha. Okay, that's the problem, but it really does escape
the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat So we get why
he didn't say like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דכתיב זבח רשע תועבה,
dichsiv zevach rasha to'eva, because זבח רשע zevach rasha explanation is the
simplest. All right, and that also is very helpful because it keeps
this in the category of של שמים, shel shamayim, but just gives
us some other reason why we're going to, you know, not redeem
it. אלא ריש לקיש מאי טעמא לא
אמר כרבי יוחנן?
ella Reish Lakish mai
ta'ama lo amar ke-Rebi Yochanan? Why did ריש לקיש Reish Lakish not
say like רבי יוחנן? Rebi Yochanan? אמר לך כי אמרינן זבח רשע
תועבה הני מילי היכא דאיתנהו בעינייהו. amar lach ki amrina zevach rasha
to'eva hani milei heicha d'isnu be'aynaihu. Look, I agree with you that
that would be a sufficient reason not to bring the קרבן, korban,
but that only applies to the קרבן korban itself. אבל הכא כיון
דאשתני אשתני, aval hacha keivan de-ishtni ishtni, that would not explain why
we don't redeem it. So if it really were like you said
רבי
יוחנן, Rebi Yochanan, that it escaped the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת
ir hanidachas. and the only reason we can't offer it up is
because of זבח רשע, zevach rasha, then if that's true, it would
not explain why we have to let it die. Because then we
would just wait for it to get a blemish and redeem it
because we actually could use the proceeds. And רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan
said no, I think you can't use the proceeds. Okay, but again
what is important here is this middle status of letting it die
by קרבנות, korbanos, two ways of going about it. fundamentally it doesn't
have a status of נדחית, nidchat, some other reason why we can't
use it, or fundamentally it does have a status of נדחית, nidchat,
but we're not going to actively destroy it. All right, let's take
a look at a little bit more. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon אומר
omer בהמתך behemtecha ולא בבכור ומעשר. velo bevchor umasser. So רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon. seems to feel that like, well, it's not clear what
he holds in general about קדשים, kadashim, but it seems to be
like you would generally hold that קדשי מזבח kadishei mizbeach are exempt,
קדשי מזבח, kadishei mizbeach, and he is coming to exempt even בכור
ומעשר. bechor umasser. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
does with this. במאי עסקינן, what are we talking about? אילימא בתמימים,
betmimim, if you're talking about בכור ומעשר bechor umasser that are unblemished,
של שמים נינהו, shel shamayim ninhu, so then and you're of the
position that קרבנות, korbanot, you know, not like the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma there, that קרבנות korbanot are fundamentally exempt, then they should be
exempt because of the של שמים shel shamayim
principle.
אלא בבעלי מומין. Ella beva'alei mumin. So, you know, why did you
need the specific פסוק passuk of בהמתך? behemtecha? So maybe what you're
talking about is that it actually has a blemish. והלכה Vehalacha of
בכור ומעשר bechor umasser are very interesting when they have a blemish.
As opposed to a normal קרבן korban when it has a blemish,
הלכה halacha is it still is, it still has to be, you
know, you can't, you know, you have to do something with the
הקדש. hekdesh So you have to redeem it on money and use
the proceeds to buy
another קרבן korban and bring the קרבן korban to the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. But בכור ומעשר bechor umasser when they have a blemish,
they actually could just be eaten outside of the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, not as a קרבן. korban. Okay, which is a fascinating הלכה.
halacha. So maybe that's what we're talking about. If that's true, שלנו
נינהו, shelanu ninhu, then they really don't have a status of a
קרבן korban and then they should be destroyed. So if they're תמימים
tmimim and they have a status of a קרבן, korban, then they
should be fundamentally excluded from the... from של שמים. shel shamayim. And
if they have a blemish, then they should be destroyed. So where
is this place where you need your פסוק passuk of בהמתך? behemtecha?
אמר
רבינא, Amar Ravina, said רבינא, Ravina, לעולם בבעלי מומין. le'olam beva'alei mumin.
We're talking that they have a blemish and nevertheless they are excluded
from the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachas Why? מי שנאכל
בתורת בהמתך. Mi shene'echal betorat behemtecha. בהמתך Behemtecha is telling you you
have to be able to eat it as you would eat any
norm... it has to be something that's fully your animal. That's the
thing you have to destroy. יצאו אלו שאינן נאכלין בתורת בהמתך אלא
בתורת בכור ומעשר. Yatzu elu she'einan ne'echalin betorat behemtecha ella betorat bechor
umasser. When you eat these things, you're still eating them as בכור
ומעשר bechor umasser and not totally as just meat. What does that
mean? So רש"י says it just means that that's what you refer
to them as. But in a different גמרא, what you, you know,
another גמרא actually has another quote and a line, it actually sounds
like there are restrictions in terms of how you sell the meat
of a בכור ומעשר. bechor umasser. So you have to watch those
הלכות halachot and they still have a status on them. You don't
have full control over them, even though you're allowed to eat them.
Okay, so this is now the principle that we've excluded fundamentally all
קרבנות korbanot from של שמים. shel shamayim. Not like the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma that seemed to say let them die, this would seem
to say maybe, you know, you have other options. And even בכור
ומעשר bechor umasser with a blemish, which should be considered like your
property, also is saved from the
הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachas אלא בתורת בכור ומעשר דשל
שמים נינהו, Ella betorat bechor umasser deshel shamayim ninhu, some take out
the גירסא girsa דשל שמים נינהו. deshel shamayim ninhu. Anyway, ופליגא דשמואל.
uphliga d'Shmuel. Now this read of רבינא Ravina
argues on שמואל's Shmuel's understanding of רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. Why? דאמר
שמואל, De'amar Shmuel, here's how שמואל Shmuel explains רב שמעון's Rav Shimon's
position. הכל קרב והכל נפדה. Hakol karev vehakol nifdeh. Everything is offered
and everything is redeemed. So that's very cryptic. מאי קאמר, Mai ka'amar,
what is he saying? הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. כל שקרב כשהוא תם
ונפדה כשהוא בעל מום משלל יצא. Kol shekarev k'shehu tam venifdeh k'shehu
ba'al mum mishalal yatza. That he's saying, this is how he explains
רב שמעון. Rav Shimon. Anything that when it's unblemished is brought as
a קרבן, korban, and when it's blemished has to be redeemed, which
is basically all קרבנות korbanot except בכור ומעשר. bechor umasser. That's in
the category of שלל שמים. shalal shamayim And that would be exempt
from עיר הנדחת ir hanidachas because of the שלל שמים shalal shamayim.
category. So why did
רב שמעון Rav Shimon need his principle of בהמתך? behemtecha? Because to
tell you the following. כל
שקרב כשהוא תם ואינו נפדה כשהוא בעל מום. Kol shekarev k'shehu tam
ve'eino nifdeh k'shehu ba'al mum. But something like בכור ומעשר, bechor umasser,
which is offered up when it's unblemished, but when it has a
blemish actually does not have to be brought as a קרבן, korban,
can just be eaten at your own table. That is not even
when it's unblemished, it's not really שלל שמים. shalal shamayim. That's a
type of a thing that's got a funny קרבן korban status. To
some degree the קדושה kedusha is not the same. You know, with
a blemish you don't have to deal with the קדושה, kedusha, you
can go ahead and eat it, you know, eat it outside the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So that type of a thing even unblemished
is not שלל שמים. shalal shamayim And that is exempt, so
מבהמה נפקא, mibeheima nafka, כגון בכור ומעשר מבהמה נפקא. kegon bechor umasser
mibeheima nafka. The only way the הלכה halacha of עיר הנדחת ir
nidachas. doesn't apply to בכור ומעשר bechor umasser is not by the
principle of שלל שמים but by the פסוק passuk of... בהמתך. Behemtecha.
This
is not, this is not fully בהמתך. Behemtecha. But here's the difference:
it's not just a דרש drash difference, it's a practical difference. What
רש״י Rashi explains is שמואל Shmuel is explaining only to רבי שמעון
that you need a separate פסוק passuk to exclude בכור Bechor and
מעשר Ma'aser when it's תם, tam, when it's brought as a קרבן.
korban. Even when it's תם, tam, it's not so much של שמים
shel shamayim and you need בהמתך. behemtecha. But if it has a
מום mum and you're eating it not as a קרבן, korban, that
actually according to רבי שמעון you would destroy. Okay, it does have
the הלכה Halacha of עיר נדחת according to שמואל'ס Shmuel's read of
רבי שמעון.
Okay, let's just do a little bit more and then we'll leave
the rest for tomorrow because we only have really one עמוד amud
tomorrow. Okay, תרומה Terumah ירקב? yirakev? Why are we letting the תרומה
Terumah rot? Okay, אמר רב חסדא: לא שנו אלא תרומה ביד ישראל.
lo shanu ela Terumah b'yad Yisrael. That's if it's in the hand
of a ישראל. Yisrael. אבל תרומה ביד כהן, Aval Terumah b'yad Kohen,
כיון דממונא הוא keivan d'mamona hu תשרף. tisaref. But once it's been
given to a כהן, Kohen, since the כהן Kohen can eat it,
that's not של שמים, shel shamayim, that actually you would burn, you
would destroy. So but the תרומה Terumah in the hand of a
ישראל, Yisrael, okay, if that's של שמים, shel shamayim, why do you
have to let it rot? That's again not clear what's this middle
state. So רש״י Rashi says well because maybe you would decide to
give it to somebody in the עיר הנדחת. So because it has
the potential of being attached to the עיר הנדחת because maybe that's
where it would have been given to, you know, that's why you
sort of have to you know and then a כהן Kohen in
the עיר הנדחת and then it would become the כהן'ס Kohen's property.
So since that's a possible would have been a possible end result,
even while it's still in the hand of ישראל, Yisrael, you can't
just walk it out of the city. You have to let it
rot. Alright, again not so explained. That's his read. Okay, so מתיב
רב יוסף. Masiv Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked on this.
מעשר שני וכתבי קודש יגנזו. Ma'aser Sheni u'kisvei kodesh yiganezu. It says
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni and scriptures you have to bury. ומעשר שני
ביד ישראל כתרומה ביד כהן דמי. u'Ma'aser Sheni b'yad Yisrael k'terumah b'yad
Kohen dami. But if a ישראל Yisrael is holding onto מעשר שני,
Ma'aser Sheni, it's like תרומה Terumah to a כהן. Kohen. Now we're
going to challenge that in a little bit but right now we're
assuming since the ישראל Yisrael can eat the מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni,
it should be like his property. So you see when you're dealing
with something that's a הקדש hekdesh grain, a הקדש hekdesh food product,
even when it's owned by the person who has the right to
eat it, we see by the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni case that
it is not fundamentally in the עיר הנדחת category to be burned
and destroyed. And if that's true about the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni
case, okay we have to figure out why it's rotting, but it's
still not actively destroyed. Then you can then that's true also about
the תרומה Terumah in the hand of a כהן. Kohen. אלא Ela
says the גמרא וקתני יגנזו v'katani yiganezu and it says יגנזו yiganezu
it does not say that you burn it. אלא אי אתמר הכי
אתמר. Ela ei ismar hachi ismar. If it was said here's how
it was said. אמר
רב חסדא לא שנו אלא תרומה ביד כהן. Amar Rav Chisda lo
shanu ela Terumah b'yad Kohen. When do we say you have to
let it rot? When it's תרומה Terumah in the hands of a
כהן. Kohen. Okay? אבל תרומה ביד ישראל, Aval Terumah b'yad Yisrael, but
if it's in the hands of a ישראל, Yisrael, then it's totally
של שמים shel shamayim and it totally escapes judgment. And what do
you do? תינתן לכהן שבעיר אחרת. tinasein l'kohen she'be'ir acheres. You give
it to a כהן Kohen that is in another city. It is
totally escaped. So again we have the question of what is the
middle state? According to number first read, you know, the middle state
was תרומה ביד ישראל, Terumah b'yad Yisrael, it is של שמים shel
shamayim but for some reason it really should escape but maybe you
would have given it to a כהן Kohen in the city or
this or that so you have to let it rot. But if
it's really if it's like really considered to be like you know
ממון בעלים mamon be'alim if it's if it's תרומה Terumah in hands
of a כהן, Kohen, then you would burn it. Okay? But that
position says that the middle state is fundamentally it's exempted but it's
still got a little problematic so we're going to let it rot.
This next answer is says no fundamentally we're talking about תרומה ביד
כהן Terumah b'yad Kohen and fundamentally it should be destroyed and it
should be burned but because it's הקדש we're going to go a
little easy. But fundamentally it does have the status of עיר הנדחת.
Just like the debate before רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish
Lakish. Is it fundamentally exempted but some reason we're not going to
walk it out of the city? Or is it fundamentally should be
burned but we're going to go a little softer? And that's what
we're saying now about that we're talking about תרומה ביד כהן. Terumah
b'yad Kohen. But תרומה ביד ישראל, Terumah b'yad Yisrael, that you can
just give it away to somebody else and that totally walks out.
Alright, let's just do a little more
here.
תנן התם. Tenan hasam. We taught over there. What's that taking on
a משנה? Anyway. עיסה של מעשר שני פטורה מן החלה. Issa shel
Ma'aser Sheni peturah min hachallah. You know, let's stop here and we
will pick up with this tomorrow.